Santa Barbara, CA, USA  $\Box$  +1 805 895 0976 ☐ alice.lepissier@gmail.com www.alicelepissier.com in alicelepissier alicelepissier walice alice.lepissier

# Alice Lépissier

Political economist and data scientist with 10+ years of experience in climate policy and international development. Specialty includes bridging research and policy interface by combining quantitative research with pragmatic policy proposals and designing intuitive tools to aid decision-making.

#### Education

- 2021 PhD, Environmental Science and Management, Bren School of Environmental Science and Management, University of California, Santa Barbara.
  - Awarded Bren School Recruitment Fellowship
  - o Research on tropical deforestation, illicit financial flows, and climate change
  - Qualifying fields: Comparative Politics and Applied Statistics
- 2020 Master of Arts, Statistics, University of California, Santa Barbara.
  - Data Science specialization
  - o GPA: 4.0
- 2011 Master of Science, Economic History, London School of Economics.
  - Awarded with Merit
  - o Dissertation: "Adaptation strategies and market responses to deal with uncertainty in rain-fed agriculture in Sub-Saharan Africa"
- 2010 Master of Science, Economics and Public Policy, Sciences Po Paris jointly with École Polytechnique.
  - o Quantitative economics program to elaborate and evaluate public policies in a wide range of contexts
  - o Events director for student organization on development in Sub-Saharan Africa · Managed 15 society members
- 2009 Bachelor of Arts, European Social and Political Studies, University College London.
  - Awarded with First Class Honors
  - Year abroad at the Universidad Complutense de Madrid

### Experience

2015-present **Consultant**, Various organizations.

- o Development of open data tool for the **Tax Justice Network** quantifying risk exposure to illicit financial flows
- Quantitative modeling of foreign direct investment and illicit financial flows for the United Nations Economic **Commission for Africa**
- o Scoping report for the Global Commission on Business and Sustainable Development on how the private sector can contribute to the Sustainable Development Goals
- o Quantitative analysis and creation of user-friendly replication tool for the Tax Justice Network on how much capital is held offshore
- 2014–2015 **Research Associate**, *Center for Global Development*, London.
  - o Lead modeler of tool SkyShares.org which allows policy-makers to compute economic costs of a climate deal
  - o Conceptualized and developed website with intuitive user interface for decision-makers
  - Quantitative and qualitative research: economic modeling, drafting policy papers and blog posts
  - o Policy outreach and engagement on climate agreements, climate finance, and illicit financial flows
- 2012–2014 **Research Assistant**, Center for Global Development, London.

Evidence-driven research on illicit financial flows and climate change to develop practical policy proposals.

Summer 2009 Consultant, LaquaR Consultants CC, Cape Town.

Research for report on Namibian sea-level rise for the Namibian Ministry of Environment and Tourism.

- Summer 2009 Research, ICLEI Africa Secretariat, Cape Town.
  - Research on climate change adaptation for the city of Cape Town.
- 2007 & 2006 Summer Internships, BRED Banque Privée, Paris, Private Wealth Management division.

# Teaching

- (x4) **POLS 15 Introduction to Research Methods**, *Department of Political Science*, Instructor of Record (Summer 2020), Teaching Assistant (Spring 2020, Spring 2019, Fall 2017).
- (x2) **ESM 210 Business and the Environment**, *Bren School of Environmental Science and Management*, Teaching Assistant (Fall 2019), Grader (Spring 2017).
- (x1) ESM 269/ED 218 Survey Design and Environmental Public Opinion, Cross-listed Bren School and Department of Education, Teaching Assistant (Spring 2018).

# Working papers

- **A. Lépissier** and M. Mildenberger. "Hybrid climate policy instruments can substantially reduce national carbon pollution".
- **A.** Lépissier, W. Davis, and G. Ibrahim. "Illicit financial flows from trade mis-invoicing in developing countries".
- A. Lépissier and A. Cobham. "Risk measures for illicit financial flows: a new international data-set".

#### **Publications**

- August 2019 Tax Justice Network report, Vulnerability and Exposure to Illicit Financial Flows in Africa.
  - AUTHORS: C. Abugre, A. Cobham, R. Etter-Phoya, A. Lépissier, M. Meinzer, N. Monkam and A. Mosioma

Available here

- December **Technical note**, "Chapter 5: Cheaper, Cooler, Faster: Reducing Tropical Deforestation for a More Cost-
  - 2016 Effective Global Response to Climate Change" In *Why Forests? Why Now? The Science, Economics, and Politics of Tropical Forests and Climate Change*, Frances Seymour and Jonah Busch. Brookings Institution Press, Washington, DC.
    - AUTHORS: J. Busch, J. Engelmann and A. Lépissier

Available here

- September CGD Policy Paper series, SkyShares: Modelling the Economic Implications of a Future Global Emissions
  - 2015 Budget, Policy Paper 067.

AUTHORS: O. Barder, A. Evans and A. Lépissier

Available here

- September **Technical paper**, *Modelling SkyShares: Technical background*.
  - 2015 AUTHORS: A. Lépissier, O. Barder and A. Evans

Available here

- June 2015 **UNA-UK report**, "A global emissions budget." In *Climate 2020 Facing the Future*, Report by the United Nations Association UK.
  - AUTHORS: O. Barder, A. Lépissier and A. Evans

Available here

- January 2015 **Contributed chapters**, *Track it! Stop it! Get it! Report of the High Level Panel on Illicit Financial Flows from Africa*, Commissioned by the AU/ECA Conference of Ministers of Finance, Planning and Economic Development.
  - AUTHORS: African Union and United Nations Economic Commission for Africa

Available here

- August 2013 **Journal of International Development**, Europe Beyond Aid: Assessing European countries' individual and collective commitment to development, Vol. 25, Issue 6.
  - AUTHORS: O. Barder, J. Clark, A. Lépissier, L. Reynolds and D. Roodman.

Available here

- December **CGD Working Paper series**, Europe Beyond Aid: Assessing Europe's commitment to development, 2012 Working Paper 313.
  - AUTHORS: O. Barder, J. Clark, A. Lépissier, L. Reynolds and D. Roodman.

Available here

## Presentations

- o "Mapping developing countries' exposure to illicit financial flows: a new data-set of risk measures", Dark Architectures: Advancing Research on Illicit Global Wealth Chains, *University of Sussex*, UK
  - "Assessing the causal impact of UK climate policy using synthetic controls: an impact analysis of the 2001 Climate Change Programme", 5th Annual Conference on Environmental Politics and Governance, University of California, Santa Barbara, USA
  - o "Mapping developing countries' exposure to illicit financial flows: a new data-set of risk measures", Development Studies Association Annual Conference 2019, *The Open University*, UK
  - "The environmental effectiveness of UK climate reforms: An impact analysis of the 2001 Climate Change Programme", Duck Family Graduate Workshop on Environmental Politics and Governance, *University of Washington*, USA
  - "Assessing the Causal Impact of Carbon Pricing Using Synthetic Control Methods: An Impact Analysis of the UK's Climate Change Programme", Bren PhD Symposium, *University of California, Santa Barbara*, USA
  - o "Trade mis-invoicing estimates in Africa", Inception Meeting on Preventing Trade Mis-invoicing in Selected African Countries, *UN Economic Commission for Africa*, Ethiopia
- 2018 Expert meeting on statistical methodologies for measuring illicit financial flows, Sustainable Development Goal 16.4.1, *UN Conference on Trade and Development*, Switzerland
- 2015 o "Ice and Climate Science Question Time with the Experts", University of Newcastle, UK
  - o "Economics of climate change: Extension or Reinvention?", Warwick Climate Forum, University of Warwick, UK
- 2014 o "How can financial markets help us tackle climate change?", University of Warwick, UK
  - o "Stakeholder perspectives on climate change adaptation", JPI Climate, Euro-Mediterranean Center on Climate Change, Italy
- 2013 o "Exposure to illicit flows in Africa", Technical Committee of the High Level Panel on Illicit Financial Flows from Africa, UN Economic Commission for Africa, Ethiopia
  - "An illicit flows target for post-2015", Conference on Illicit Financial Flows, Academics Stand Against Poverty, UK
- 2010 o Interview with Youssou N'Dour about African development, *Sciences Po Paris*, France Event filmed for Senegalese television · Organized the event & negotiated free concert · 200 attended

#### Professional courses

Feb 2014 Practical General Equilibrium Modeling with GAMS

Impartica IT Training, Leeds, UK

June 2013 Panel Data Analysis using Stata

Timberlake, London, UK

EcoMod, Boston, MA

### Computing

June 2013 SQL Data Management

Methods econometrics  $\cdot$  machine learning  $\cdot$  deep learning  $\cdot$  Integrated Assessment Modeling  $\cdot$  website development  $\cdot$  user experience design  $\cdot$  database management

Selected SkyShares (JavaScript) · Bézier spline interpolation (Visual Basic) · Illicit financial flows (Stata) · Genetic repositories algorithm (R)

### Languages

Fluent French (native) · Spanish · English

Conversational Italian

# Other writing and service activity

- Op-ed "Global goals can deliver on 2°C and new development finance here's how", The Guardian, 9/24/15.
- Blogging Various posts on Views from the Center for Global Development, including "Setting a Price on Carbon Immediately Is Necessary to Avoid Dangerous Climate Change" and "A Global Carbon Tax or Cap-and-Trade? Part 1: The Economic Arguments".
- Referee Journal of Environment and Development, Climatic Change
- Service Coordinator of the "Sustaining Movement Momentum and Building Political Power" conference, June 2017, University of California Santa Barbara
- Service Advisor to Master's group project: "Prioritizing restorative wood products by market readiness, climate impact and carbon storage potential", Bren School of Environmental Science and Management
- Service Search committee for tenure-track Lecturer in Environmental Data Science, 2020, Bren School
- Service Search committee for Assistant Professor in Environmental Data Science, 2020, Bren School

# Awards and fellowships

- 2020 Central Campus Dissertation Fellowship, Graduate Division, University of California Santa Barbara
- 2020 Nominee for Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award, Academic Senate, University of California Santa Barbara
- 2020 Graduate Student Research Fellow, National Socio-Environmental Synthesis Center (SESYNC)
- 2019 H. William Kuni Fellowship, Bren School of Environmental Science and Management
- 2017 Energy and Climate Graduate Fellow of the Scholars Strategy Network
- 2016 Bren School of Environmental Science and Management Recruitment Fellowship
- 2016 International Doctoral Recruitment Fellowship, University of California Santa Barbara
- 2006 Sessional Prize for academic merit, University College London

#### Grants

- 2020 "Financial Opacity and Challenges to Forest Governance in Indonesia and Malaysia", National Socio-Environmental Synthesis Center (SESYNC), co-PI on Graduate Pursuit
- 2016 "The economic prize for business of achieving the Sustainable Development Goals", Business and Sustainable Development Commission, research grant number BSDC-02
- 2016 "The Price of Offshore, robust replication", Tax Justice Network, research grant
- 2013 "The Political Economy of Illicit Financial Flows in Africa and their Impact on Africa's Development", United Nations Economic Commission for Africa, grant with Alex Cobham, \$25,000

#### References

#### Owen Barder

CEO

Precision Agriculture for Development

#### Matthew Potoski

Professor of Corporate Environmental Management Assistant Professor of Political Science UC Santa Barbara

#### Alex Cobham

CEO

Tax Justice Network

☑ alex@taxjustice.net

#### Matto Mildenberger

UC Santa Barbara

for 3 years

for 3 years